A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z FA394
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA394
41.83 Cubic Feet Boxes 423-535. 104 letter document boxes, 8 half-letter document boxes, 1 legal box and 26 microfilm boxes (35mm)
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation officers' diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential. The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
Conditions Governing Access note
Each set of officers' diaries is open for research 20 years after the date of the last diary entry.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by surname.
Philanthropy -- United States; Humanities; Epidemics; Medical sciences; Philanthropy; Life sciences; Race and society; Public health; African Americans; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Arts; Diseases; Charities
- Salant, Walter S., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1960-1961 (Box 423)
- Sanders, Alvin Joyner, 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1971-1972 (Box 423)
  - 1973 (Box 423)
- Sanders, Morris B., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1931-1932 (Box 424)
- Sandt, Donald G., Jr., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1968-1970 (Box 424)
- Sasse, Bruce E., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1949-1954 (Box 424)
- Saxton, George A., 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - 1963-1967 (Box 424)
- Sawyer, Wilbur A., 1.18 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes and 3 microfilm boxes (35mm)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files and user copies of the microfilm are available for access.
  Africa; South America; Asia; Australia
  - Reports, 1924-1925, 1930 (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 1)
  - Report on Ceylon Part 1, February 22, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 16 pages
    Sri Lanka; Sanitation; Public health; Hygiene; Hookworm disease
  - Report on Ceylon Part 2, March 17, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 22 pages
    Malaria; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Sri Lanka; Sanitation; Public health
  - Report on Ceylon Part 3, March 21, 1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 14 pages
  - Report on Trip to Madras Presidency, April 28,1924; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 18 pages
    Sanitation; Medicine, Preventive; Public health; India; Medical education; Hookworm disease; Hygiene
  - Report on Trip to Calcutta, Santiniketan, and Bombay, May 3, 1924; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 10 pages
    Scope and Contents note
    Brief report addressed to Dr. Victor G. Heiser, Director for the East, International Board of Health regarding local Malaria Campaigns. Sawyer interviews professionals in the field of public health, tours and surveys medical facilities and education.
    Hygiene; Sanitation; Medical education; Public health; India; Malaria
  - Report on Visit to Venezuela, June 12, 1925; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 13 pages
    Brief report addressed to Dr. F.F. Russell, General Director International Health Board regarding tropical diseases in Venezuela. Sawyer interviews professionals in the field of public health regarding Malaria, Hookworm and Sanitation in Caracas.
    Malaria; Sanitation; Public health; Venezuela; Hookworm disease
  - Trip of Inspection of Yellow Fever Activities in Brazil, May 15, 1930; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 11 pages
    A brief report made by Sawyer regarding Yellow Fever activities in Brazil.
    Brazil; Yellow fever; Public health
  - Trip of Inspection of Yellow Fever Activities in Brazil, May 25, 1930; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; 32 pages
    Public health; Brazil; Yellow fever
  - 1924-1928, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 414 pages (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 157)
    The diaries are arranged by interview and visit. From 1924-1926, Sawyer is the director of the International Health Board Public Health Laboratory Service. These entries concern Rockefeller Foundation laboratories, meetings with professionals in the field of public health and conferences pertaining to hookworm. In 1926, Sawyer goes on assignment to the West African Yellow Fever Commission, Lagos, Nigeria. In west Africa he documents laboratory research various field studies on the symptomology and pathology of Yellow Fever Includes "Localities infected with yellow fever in 1926" chart.
    In 1927, Sawyer becomes the associate director of Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division.
    In 1935, Sawyer becomes director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division after Fredrick F. Russell retires. This diary is organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects, research and proposals. He is involved in administrative duties of the International Health Division. This diary includes a 1935 index.
    The 1936 diary is organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects, research and proposals. He is involved in administrative duties of the International Health Division. This diary includes a 1936 index.
    Diaries; Nigeria; Medicine, Preventive; Malaria; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Ghana; Yellow fever; Vaccines; Urine -- Analysis; United States; Tropical medicine; Public health
  - Index, 1935 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 395, Box 425)
  - 1935 (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 399)
  - Index, 1936 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 442, Box 425)
  - 1936 (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 452, Box 425)
  - Index to Trip with Dr. Warren Acting Director, 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 4 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 608, Box 425)
    1937 Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
    indexes (reference sources)
  - 1937, Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 25 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 612, Box 425)
    Brief diary notes of Andrew J. Warren acting for Wilbur A. Sawyer. Arranged by interview.
    Diaries; United States; Public health
  - Index (Excluding Visit to Far East), 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 8 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 637, Box 425)
    1937 Index; 8 pages; alphabetical
  - Visit to the Far East, 1937; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Peking Union Medical College; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 217 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Sawyer visits the Far East and surveys the health insurance, medical education and facilities in Asia. The diary discusses the Asian RF programs.
    Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Philippines; Diaries; Public health; Medical education; Microbiology; Yellow fever; Japan; Hygiene; Malaria; Java; China; United States; Health insurance
  - Index (Excluding Visits), 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 8 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 863, Box 425)
    1938 Index; 8 pages; alphabetical
    Public health; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1937 December 8- 1938 June 30, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 1 page (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 871, Box 425)
    Front page of diary.
    Diaries; Public health
  - Index- Trip to India, Ceylon, Africa, and England, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 10 pages
    1938 Index; 10 pages; arranged by visit and interview
  - Trip to India, Ceylon, Africa and England, 8 December 1937 - 21 February 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 66 pages
    Cholera; Egypt; England; Tropical medicine; Malaria; Medical education; Nursing; Rice; France; Hygiene; India; Irrigation; Sri Lanka; Diaries
  - Index - Andrew J. Warren Acting for Wilbur A. Sawyer, 1938 January 3- June 30; Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 4 pages (Reel M Saw 1, Frame 948, Box 425)
    Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
    Medical education; Malaria; indexes (reference sources); Tropical medicine; United States; Yellow fever; Microbiology; Nursing; Public health; Rabies
  - 1938 Andrew J Warren Acting, 1938 January 3- June 30; Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 101 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Sawyer in this 1938 diary talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Includes a letter addressed to Dr. John B. Grant from Raymond B. Fosdick.
    Public health; Rabies; Tropical medicine; United States; Malaria; Medical education; Microbiology; Nursing; Diaries; Yellow fever
  - 1938 July 1- December 30, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 1 page (Box 425, Reel M Saw 1, Frame 1,055)
    1 page
    Diaries; Public health; Medical education
  - 1938 Diary Notes for July, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 44 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, these RVR notes for July through September 1938 diary talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. It includes indexes for July and September.
    Public health; Medical education
  - Index Trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 5 pages
    1938 Index; 5 pages; arranged by visit and interview
    Jamaica; Malaria; indexes (reference sources); Influenza; Public health; Tropical medicine; Microbiology; Panama; Tuberculosis; United States; Colombia; Yellow fever; Cuba; Costa Rica
  - Trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba, 1938 September 3- December 30; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 75 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer takes a trip to Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica, Jamaica and Cuba to survey research proposals and Rockefeller Foundation programs. He talks to professionals in the field as well as Rockefeller Foundation officers.
    Yellow fever; Colombia; Cuba; Costa Rica; Influenza; Malaria; Jamaica; Panama; Microbiology; Tropical medicine; Public health; United States; Tuberculosis; Diaries
  - Trip Index to Puerto Rico Visit, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 2 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 1)
    1939 Index; 2 pages; arranged by visit and interview
  - Trip to Puerto Rico, 1939 January 9-19; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 9 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 3)
    Sawyer surveys and tours public health facilities that help combat tuberculosis in this brief trip.
    Diaries; United States; Tuberculosis; Tropical medicine; Puerto Rico; Public health
  - Index, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 11 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 12)
    1939 Index; 11 pages; alphabetical
  - Index of Diary for Dr. Strode Acting for Dr. Sawyer, 1939; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Strode, George K. (1886-1958); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 4 pages
    1939 Index; 4 pages; alphabetical
  - 1939 January 3-May 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 115 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 27)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research.
    Malaria; Diaries; Yellow fever; United States; Tuberculosis; Public health; Nutrition; Microbiology; Medicine, Preventive
  - 1939 May 31-December 30, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 154 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 153, Box 426)
    Medicine, Preventive; Microbiology; Nutrition; Public health; Syphilis; Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Typhus fever; United States; Venereal diseases; Yellow fever; Hygiene; Diaries; Malaria; Influenza
  - Index, 1940; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 13 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 200, Box 426)
    General note
    This frame number is unconfirmed.
    1940 Index; 10 pages; alphabetical
    indexes (reference sources); Public health
  - 1940 George K. Strode Acting, Strode, George K. (1886-1958); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 27 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, George K. Strode acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During April 5, 1940-May 17, 1940, Strode is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    United States; Zoology; Diaries; Nutrition; Public health; Medicine; Nursing; Hygiene
  - 1940 January 2-April 4, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 79 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 317)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research. A discussion with the American Red Cross take place regarding IHD interests in Europe relating to refuges, nutrition, typhus and World War II.
    World War II; Hygiene; Nursing; Nutrition; Influenza; Malaria; Sanitation; Syphilis; Public health; Refugees; United States; Vaccines; Tropical medicine; Typhus fever
  - 1940 Index Trip to Europe, 1940 April 5- May 16; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 5 pages
    1940 Index; 5 pages; arranged by interview and visit
    indexes (reference sources); Europe; Public health
  - 1940 Trip to Europe, 1940 April 5- May 16; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); 46 pages; 47 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During April 5, 1940-May 17, 1940, Sawyer is visiting Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war.
    Diaries; Belgium; World War II; Hygiene; France; Europe; England; Refugees; Public health; Portugal; Influenza; Vaccines; Typhus fever; Spain
  - 1940 May 16-December 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 73 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 474, Box 426)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As Director of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division, he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties. The focus of the diary is the discussion of current and future public health related research. IHD interests in Europe relating to World War II id discussed.
    Hygiene; Influenza; Malaria; Yellow fever; World War II; Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Typhus fever; United States; Microbiology; Nursing; Nutrition; Public health; Vaccines; Diaries
  - Trip to Europe Index, 1940; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 6 pages
    France; Europe; Public health; Spain; indexes (reference sources); Portugal; United States
  - Trip to Europe, 1940 August 4- September 9; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During August 4, 1940-September 9 1940, Sawyer is visiting Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war.
    Portugal; Public health; Hygiene; Malaria; United States; Vaccines; Spain; Typhus fever; World War II; Diaries; Europe; France
  - 1940 4 August- 13 December, Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1940 August 4- December 13; Warren, Andrew J.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 104 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During 4 August- 13 December 1940, Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    Diaries; Vaccines; United States; Yellow fever; Malaria; Influenza; Tropical medicine; Public health; Typhus fever; Tuberculosis
  - 1940 14-31 December Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1940 December 14- 31; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 6 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. During 14-31 December 1940, Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office.
    Nutrition; United States; Public health; Yellow fever; Vaccines
  - Index, 1941; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951) (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 711, Box 426)
    1941 Index; 13 pages; alphabetical
  - 1940 December 14- 1941 March 10, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 94 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 724, Box 426)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. He visits Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war. The dairy documents Sawyer's tours and surveys laboratories, public health programs and medical facilities.
    Diaries; Nursing; Influenza; Hygiene; France; Europe; England; Yellow fever -- Vaccination; Typhus fever; Tropical medicine; Spain; Public health; Portugal; Nutrition
  - 1941 1 January- 29 June- Andrew J. Warren Acting- Diary, 1941 January 1- June 29; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    United States; Vaccines; Nutrition; Public health; Malaria; Nursing; Diaries; Influenza; Yellow fever
  - 1941 June 30-August 5, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation; 17 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 948)
    Diaries
  - 8 July- 31 December Diary-Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1941 July 8- December 31; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 198 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. He attends various conferences on epidemic diseases.
    Yellow fever; Vaccines; United States; Typhus fever; Sanitation; Nutrition; Public health; Influenza; Diaries; Malaria; Hygiene
  - Index, 1942; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 1, Box 427)
    1942 Index; 13 pages; alphabetical
    United States; Public health
  - 1942 January 2-March 20, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 14, Box 427)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. The focus of the International Health Divison's health phase of the war effort includes perfecting the yellow fever vaccine, nutrition, influenza vaccine, studies in typhus and syphilis which all fall under the Divison's larger mission of disease prevention, health services and support for public health education.
    Dysentery; Yellow fever; Vaccines; United States; Typhus fever; Syphilis; Public health; Malaria; Louse; Influenza
  - 1942 March 20-May 29, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 108, Box 427)
    One page
    Public health; United States
  - 20 March-22 April Trip to California Index, 1942 20 March-22; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951)
    Public health; United States; Yellow fever; Jaundice
  - 20 March-22 April- Trip to California, 1942 20 March-22 April; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (1879-1951); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    California; Jaundice; Public health; United States; Yellow fever